{"tossups": [{"question": "This country\u2019s troops renamed Fort Casimir as Fort Trinity after its capture. This European power exclusively traded firearms to their Native American allies, the Susquehannocks. This country built the first colony along the Delaware River at present-day Wilmington during a voyage in which this country\u2019s people were led by the Dutch captain Peter Minuit. Log cabins were introduced to North America by this country, whose colonial ambitions were e\u21b5ectively ended when Peter Stuyvesant captured Fort Christina. For the point, name this country that colonized what is now Bridgeport, New Jersey as \u201cNew Stockholm.\u201d", "answer": "<b> Sweden</b> (accept New<b> Sweden</b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "Description acceptable. According to one legend, the first holder of this position was given a golden sta\u21b5to mark the place where a temple was to be created. Titu Cusi held this position before a successor who was attacked by Francisco de Toledo in the Vilcabamba Valley; that holder of this position inspired the name of a 1781 rebellion against a Viceroyalty. The first holder of this position was Manco Capac. Tupac Amaru was the last holder of, for the point, what position, the ruler of a major Peruvian empire?", "answer": "<b> Sapa</b> Inca (accept<b> emperor</b>,<b> king</b>, etc.; of the<b> Incas</b> or equivalents indicating the<b> leader of Incas</b>; accept<b> Sapa</b>; accept<b> Inka Qhapaq</b>; accept<b> Apu</b>) Page 2", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "Benjamin Thorpe edited six sections of this work for the Rolls Series. A subsection of this text was destroyed in a fire at a church in Peterborough. An unusually lengthy section of this work describes Sigeberht\u2019s death at the hands of Cynewulf. This work introduced<em> bretwalda</em>, a kingly title held by Raedwald of East Anglia and seven others, and was partially translated by the bishop Asser. For the point, name this text, composed under Alfred the Great in the 9th century, that chronicles the history of the group that dominated England prior to the Norman Conquest.", "answer": "The<b> Anglo-Saxon Chronicle</b>s", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Benjamin, a politician with this surname, managed the<em> New York Daily News</em> for forty years in the late 1800s. When George Walling attempted to arrest a politician with this surname, he called in the Municipal police force, causing a police riot; that politician, Fernando, was a two-time Democratic mayor of New York City. Theodore Roosevelt was second in command to a military officer of this surname in a cavalry corps active in the Spanish-American War. For the point, give this surname of Leonard, the leader of the Rough Riders.", "answer": "<b> Wood</b> (accept Benjamin<b> Wood</b>; accept Fernando<b> Wood</b>; accept Leonard<b> Wood</b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "Charles Fabry and Alfred Perot developed an instrument crucial to the operation of this project, which had to achieve seismic isolation. Ronald Drever was a co-founder of this project, but passed away seven months before a Nobel Prize was awarded for it. Proposed following the work of Rainer Weiss and Kip Thorne, this project was the largest NSF-funded endeavor of all time. Caltech and MIT jointly operate this project, which has detectors in Washington and Louisiana that have observed black hole collisions. For the point, name this project that finally detected gravitational waves in 2015.", "answer": "<b> Laser</b> <b>Interferometer</b> <b>Gravitational-Wave</b> <b>Observatory</b> (or<b> LIGO</b>; prompt on descriptive answers related to \u201cthe project to observe gravitational waves\u201d before mentioned)", "metadata": "Science - Physics"}, {"question": "This man pointed out that vertical integration and price discrimination were punished despite not harming consumers in his book<em> The Antitrust Paradox</em>. Ted Kennedy claimed that, in this man\u2019s America,\u201d women would be forced into back-alley abortions and blacks would sit at segregated lunch counters.\u201d As Solicitor General, this man ultimately carried out Nixon\u2019s order to fire special prosecutor Archibald Cox. Anthony Kennedy received his highest post after only 42 Senators voted to confirm, for the point, what man whose 1987 nomination to the Supreme Court was rejected?", "answer": "Robert<b> Bork</b> Page 3", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "In this year, Eli Hart\u2019s store was attacked by a mob in the Flour Riot. A stunning Whig electoral victory in this year\u2019s state-level elections was dubbed a \u201cNew York tornado\u201d by the sitting president. In this year, Congress began talks about a Divorce Bill to create an independent treasury system. The president who was inaugurated in this year received the nickname \u201cruin,\u201d as hundreds of banks failed in the second nationwide economic panic in American history. For the point, name this year of Martin van Buren\u2019s inauguration.", "answer": "<b> 1837</b> (accept Panic of<b> 1837</b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "A novel by this author includes the Witchcraft scheme, whereby one man trades valuable information, or gold dust, for worthless information, or chicken feed. In a novel by this author, Liz Gold is shot and killed while crossing an international border and The Circus uses Alec Leamas as their unwitting pawn to protect a former Nazi. A nursery rhyme about a \u201crich man, poor man, / beggarman, thief\u201d provides the title of a novel by this author in which Control tasks George Smiley with finding a mole. For the point, name this member of Britain\u2019s MI6 and author of the Cold War-era novels<em> The Spy Who Came in from</em> <em>the Cold</em> and<em> Tinker Tailor Soldier Spy</em>.", "answer": "John<b> le Carre</b> (accept David<b> Cornwell</b>)", "metadata": "Literature - British Literature - Short Fiction"}, {}, {"question": "An event named after this type of location was investigated by the fraudulent Burdenko Commission and by the writer Ferdynand Goetel. A battle named after this type of location culminated in a massacre near Kalkriese Hill, where heavy rains bogged down three legions under the command of Publius Varus. The NKVD executed thousands of Polish officers and buried them in one of these locations named Katyn [kah-TEEN]. Germanic tribesmen under the command of Arminius won a battle named after the Teutoberg type of this location. Fortifications in the spa town of Baden-Baden are found in, for the point, the Black example of what type of wooded area?", "answer": "<b> forest</b>s (or<b> wald</b>; accept Katyn<b> Forest</b> Massacre; accept Battle of Teutoberg<b> Forest</b>; accept Black<b> Forest</b>) Page 4", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Antonia Novello was the first woman to hold this position, in which capacity she criticized advertising mascots like Old Joe. Joycelyn Elders was a controversial holder of this position under Bill Clinton who proposed the legalization of drugs to stop crime. Holders of this position included C. Everett Koop, who authored a report on the psychological e\u21b5ects of abortion, and Luther Terry, who released a 1964 study that linked cigarette smoking to various diseases. For the point, name this position in the federal government held by a public health expert.", "answer": "US<b> Surgeon General</b>", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "This leader described the invasion of Czechoslovakia as a \u201cserious danger to peace in Europe\u201d in the 21st of August speech. This leader, who overhauled his security forces after the defection of Ion Pacepa, called for a \u201cmini cultural revolution\u201d in his July Theses and heavily restricted access to contraceptives as part of his Decree 770. The eviction order of pastor Laszlo Tokes [toh-kesh] led to protests against this leader in Timisoara [ti-mish-wara]. This leader was overthrown and executed by a firing squad with his wife Elena on Christmas Day 1989. For the point, name this former Communist dictator of Romania.", "answer": "Nicolae<b> Ceausescu</b> [cho-chess-koo]", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "A type of ensemble from this country, featuring the oboe-like zurna and the davul, was known as the mehteran. Mozart\u2019s<em> Violin Concerto no. 5</em> was nicknamed for this country, and specially-manufactured pianos often played his<em> Piano Sonata no. 11</em>, which ends with a rondo named for this country. Triangles, bass drums, and cymbals were imported into Western orchestras from this country following its wars with the Hapsburg Empire. For the point, a Classical-era craze for the music of what country was inspired by the Janissary military bands of the Ottoman Empire?", "answer": "<b> Turkey</b> (accept<b> Ottoman Empire</b> before mentioned)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {}, {}, {"question": "This person\u2019s home country gave out its first passport to send this person to Moscow as minister to Russia in 1948. This leader lost power after being cleared by the Agranat Commission, though this leader\u2019s reputation was still tarnished by the weak response to a troop buildup on the Golan Heights. For the point, name this Israeli prime minister during the Yom Kippur War, the only woman to have held the post.", "answer": "Golda<b> Meir</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "The Cuyahoga River [kye-ah-ho-gah river] flows into Lake Erie in, for the point, what city, home to Case Western Reserve University in northeastern Ohio?", "answer": "<b> Cleveland</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "After the McClellan Committee investigated this man, George Meany essentially ordered this man\u2019s removal from power. This man\u2019s son contested Ron Carey\u2019s electoral defeat shortly after Carey had led that man\u2019s union in a 1997 UPS strike. This man negotiated the National Master Freight Agreement that extended protections to over 450,000 drivers. After meeting two Mafia men at the Red Fox Restaurant in 1975, this man mysteriously disappeared. For the point, name this leader of the Teamsters.", "answer": "James \u201cJimmy\u201d R.<b> Ho\u21b5a</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "A series of fortifications at this battle were named for London, Rouen and Paris. Prior to this battle, Robert de Baudricourt met with this engagement\u2019s most famous participant three times. Jean of Dunois [zhahn of doo-nwah] led a defense in this battle against William de la Pole. Following this battle, a series of battles, including one at Patay, were fought in the Loire Campaign. During this battle, John Talbot ended his attack after Fort St. Loup fell. The Battle of the Herrings proceeded, for the point, what 1428-29 siege that was broken by the arrival of Joan of Arc?", "answer": "Siege of<b> Orleans</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "Two answers required. After a scientific breakthrough in one of these two countries, the leader of the other gave a speech stating that \u201cThe East Wind Prevails Over the West.\u201d One of these two countries allied with Albania in defiance of the other after denouncing the other as \u201crevisionist\u201d because of the\u201cSecret Speech.\u201d One of these two countries withdrew its advisors to the other after its policy of \u201cpeaceful coexistance\u201d was criticized during the Great Leap Forward. For the point, name these two countries that\u201csplit\u201d in the 1960s, despite being the largest Communist countries in the world.", "answer": "People\u2019s Republic of<b> China</b> and the<b> Soviet Union</b> (accept<b> Union of Soviet Socialist Republics</b> or<b> USSR</b> or<b> CCCP</b> or<b> SSSR</b> for \u201cSoviet Union;\u201d accept<b> Zhonghua Renmin Gongheguo </b>or<b> Zhongguo</b> for \u201cChina;\u201d accept descriptions of the<b> Sino-Soviet</b> Split; prompt on \u201cRussia\u201d for \u201cSoviet Union\u201d)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This nation saw the rise of the ultra-nationalist Mkhedrioni, or \u201cHorsemen,\u201d which launched a successful coup against its first president, Zviad Gamsakhurdia [z\u2019vee-ahd gahm-sah-kurd-ee-uh]. This nation, which heavily shelled the city of Sukhumi in a 1992-1993 war, had its longtime president Eduard Shevardnadze peacefully deposed by protesters and replaced by Mikhail Saakashvili in the Rose Revolution. For the point, name this country that does not recognize the Republic of South Ossetia, which broke away from this country with Russian assistance.", "answer": "<b> Georgia</b> Page 8", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This city was the subject of a 2014 Ben Reiter prediction that proved true despite a mishap involving Mark Appel. This city\u2019s baseball team signed the first million-dollars-per-year MLB contract and built the world\u2019s first domed stadium. Another sport created a lottery system after a team from this city \u201ctanked\u201dto win the first pick in the 1984 draft; that team\u2019s current General Manager, Daryl Morey, names an o\u21b5ense that relies on three pointers and layups and was led by James Harden to the Western Conference\u2019s best record in 2018. For the point, name this city, home to basketball\u2019s Rockets and baseball\u2019s defending champion Astros.", "answer": "<b> Houston</b> (accept<b> Houston</b> Astros; accept<b> Houston</b> Rockets after \u201clottery\u201d is read) <b>Extra Question</b> Only read if moderator botches a question.", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "A Christian Democratic President of this country launched reforms like \u201csocial promotion,\u201dagrarian reform, and education reform; later, that President backed the electoral opponent of Jorge Alessandri. Marcelo Moren Brito operated a torture facility at the Villa Grimaldi in this country. The apolitical nature of this country\u2019s military was briefly upheld by the Schneider Doctrine. One leader of this country operated a \u201cCaravan of Death,\u201d which used helicopters to execute political opponents. For the point, name this country that has been led by Salvador Allende and Augusto Pinochet.", "answer": "<b> Chile</b> Page 9", "metadata": "History - World History"}], "bonuses": []}